1981年4月14日
On the 14th of April 1981,
航天飞机成功完成首飞
the Space Shuttle completed its first successful flight
着陆在加利福尼亚州爱德华兹空军基地
and landed back at Edwards Air Force Base in California.
经过数年的研发与数十亿美元的投资
After years of development and billions of dollars,
这款当时世界上最强的航天运载器正式投入使用
the world's most capable space vehicle was now in operation.
未来的航天道路一片光明
And the future of spaceflight looked very promising.
停一下
But wait a minute.
其实这不是加州 也不是1981年 也不是美国的航天飞机
That's not California, that's not 1981, and that isn't the Space Shuttle.
实际上这里是1988年的哈萨克斯坦
In fact, this is Kazakhstan in 1988.
在十余年的时间里 苏联一直在秘密研究他们自己的航天飞机 暴风雪号
For over a decade, the Soviet Union had been secretly working on their own space plane called the Буран,
它的外观和美国的航天飞机非常接近
which had a remarkable resemblance to the Space Shuttle.
凭借几乎相同的形状和颜色方案
With an almost identical shape and color scheme,
很明显 苏联人从美国的航天飞机上获得了很多灵感
it was clear that the Soviets had taken a lot of inspiration from America's Shuttle.
但大家并不清楚苏联人是如何如此迅速地复制设计并追上美国人的
But it wasn't clear
how the Soviets managed to copy the design and catch up to the American so quickly.
在太空方面 美国和苏联有着非常激烈的竞争历史
The US and the Soviet Union already had a history of intense competition when it came to space.
苏联人拿下了发射人类第一颗卫星的记录
The Soviets took the record for launching the first satellite into orbit,
而美国人则搞了个登月予以还击
and then America managed to beat them to the moon.
但他们同时又有过一段良好的合作
But they also had periods of healthy cooperation.
在1975年的阿波罗-联盟号计划中
With the Apollo Soyuz project in 1975,
两国将各自的飞船在轨对接
both nations joined their two spacecraft together in orbit,
两边的宇航员一起生活了一周
where crews from both sides lived for a week.
而在这之前一年 暴风雪号的故事就已悄然开始
But it was 1 year before this where the Буран story begins.
在一次克里姆林宫的秘密会议中
During a secret meeting at the Kremlin,
当时的苏联负责人列昂尼德·斯米尔诺夫
the head of the Soviet military, Смирнов Леонид,
与苏联领导人勃列日涅夫会面 讨论下一年的首要任务
met with Soviet leader Бре́жнев to discuss the top priorities for the following year.
这次会议与往常一样 简单汇报工作 让苏联领导人了解一下最新情况
This meeting was like any other, a simple catch up to keep the Soviet leader up to date on things.
但在会议结束时
But at the end of the meeting,
斯米尔诺夫提醒勃列日涅夫 美国人正在研究一款带翼太空飞行器
Смирнов alerted Бре́жнев that the Americans were working on a winged space vehicle,
对苏联将是一个强大威胁
which would be a strong threat to the Soviet Union.
他认为美国人研究的很可能是一款能够快速变轨
He believed that whatever they were working on was capable of quickly changing orbit
很快就到你家门口的高度危险武器
and positioning itself directly over Moscow, possibly full of dangerous weapons.
在当时 NASA的航天飞机其实刚开始设计没几年
This point in time, NASA's Space Shuttle designs were only a few years old,
但总体概念已经确定下来了
but the general concept had been decided on.
意识到自己这边至少落后几年后
Realizing that they were at least a few years behind,
苏联领导人勃列日涅夫决定必须采取行动了
Soviet leader Бре́жнев decided that something had to be done.
他希望苏联能建造一个比美国航天飞机更有强力的航天器
He wanted the Soviet Union to build a spacecraft that would be even more capable than the Shuttle.
于是拨出巨额资金 启动了暴风雪项目
So an enormous amount of money was set aside and project Буран was initiated.
军方开始和各大设计局交涉
The military started reaching out to the OKB,
他们是为军方设计制造一些先进技术原型的一堆私有机构
a collection of private institutions,
which would design and prototype advanced technologies, usually for the military.
众所周知 苏联的太空项目全世界都是数一数二的
It was no secret that the Soviet space program was one of the best in the world,
手下有数万科学家和工程师
with tens of thousands of scientists and engineers.
尽管此时该项目已经正式开始
Although the project was officially underway by this point,
但苏联人还没有确定设计方案
the Soviets hadn't settled on a design yet.
他们找到了自己60年代的一个废弃项目
They were looking at one of their discarded projects from the 60s,
里面有一款叫"螺旋"的可复用航天飞机
which featured a reusable space plane called the Spiral.
这个项目曾短暂地重启过一段时间 但很快又被军方取消了
After briefly bringing the project back to life, it was quickly canceled again by the military.
因为他们知道它没有美国人做的那么先进
As they knew it wasn't as advanced as what the Americans were doing.
苏联人意识到他们需要了解他们试图击败的对手更多信息
The Soviets realized that they needed to know more about the vehicle they were trying to beat.
令人惊讶的是 航天飞机项目并没有被列为机密
Surprisingly, the Shuttle program wasn't classified,
每一个设计和研究文件基本都是对大众公开的
so every design and research paper was essentially available to the public.
苏联人的问题是要去整理这些海量的数据
The problem for the Soviets was the sheer amount of data and finding a way to organize it.
但这已经不是苏联人第一次将各种技术数据做汇总了
But this wasn't the first time the Soviets set out together technical data.
早在60年代 他们就成功渗透进了英法的协和飞机制造商
In the 60s, they successfully spied on the British and French Concorde manufacturers
以生产他们自己版本的超音速喷气式客机图-144
to produce their own version of the supersonic jet liner, known as the TU-144.
但这次间谍活动的主要优势之一是最近发明的互联网
But one of the main advantages in this case of espionage was the recent invention of the internet.
虽然在当时还非常基础
Although it was very basic at the time,
但NASA在网上数据库中储存了许多关键文件
NASA was storing many of its critical documents in online databases.
因此 为了获得这些文件并将数据传回给苏联工程师
And so, in order to obtain these documents and funnel the data back to the Soviet engineers,
他们叫来了克格勃帮忙
they called upon the service of the KGB.
监督这个间谍项目的大部分工作的是一个名叫弗拉基米尔·维特洛夫的间谍
Overseeing the majority of this espionage project was a spy named Владимир Ветров.
他从年轻的时候就一直在克格勃工作 当时他还住在法国
He began working with the KGB at an early age while living in France
并一步步努力爬上了克格勃最高级别的成员之一
and eventually worked his way up to being one of the highest ranking members.
他是这项工作的完美人选
He was the perfect man for the job.
苏联也很清楚自己需要什么
The Soviets knew exactly what they needed.
他们正在寻找有关航天飞机的机身、飞行、计算机、材料和推进系统的信息
They were looking for information
regarding the Shuttle's airframe, flight, computers, materials, and the propulsion system.
在莫斯科的苏联商会里
Back at the Soviet Chamber of Commerce in Moscow,
他们有自己的先进计算机中心
they had their own advanced computer center.
苏联人使用它就能进入美国的在线信息服务
With this, the Soviets were able to tap into American's online information services
看到与航天飞机有关的文件的名称和编号
and see the names and numbers of Shuttle related documents.
有了这些信息 克格勃特工只需离开苏联驻华盛顿大使馆
With this information, a KGB agent would simply leave the Soviet embassy in Washington
前往位于首都北街的政府印刷办公室
and make their way to the government printing office on North capital street.
他们告诉政府工作人员需要的文件的名称和编号
They would tell the government worker the name and number of the document they needed,
然后支付印刷费 再把文件带回大使馆
pay the printing fee, and then take the documents back to the embassy.
苏联人可能每次带回重要文件的时候都会庆祝一下
At this point, the Soviets probably had a party
every time they came back with an important document.
但所有重要的技术资料还需要在美国不知道的情况下送回给苏联的工程师们
But all the important technical information
still had to be sent back to the Soviet engineers without the US knowing about it.
第一步是将数据带离美国
The first step was getting it out of America.
他们的办法是将文件的电子版送到维也纳和赫尔辛基的研究中心
They chose to send the documents electronically to research centers in Vienna and Helsinki,
这比直接将文件送到苏联来带的怀疑要少得多
much less suspicious than sending them directly to the Soviet Union.
克格勃的工作人员随后会把文件转发到莫斯科
From there, KGB workers would forward the documents to Moscow
在那里 一屋子的打印机会昼夜不停地运转 打印出数据文件
where a room full of printers would be working around the clock, constantly producing the goods.
对于苏联人来说 在防热材料上的研究是非常重要的
For the Soviets, the research on heat shield material was of high importance.
但最大的突破之一是找到航天飞机的风洞数据
But one of the biggest breakthroughs was finding the Shuttles wind tunnel data.
这也最终是苏联人完全复制了航天飞机外形的原因
This is ultimately why the Soviets completely copied the Shuttle's shape,
因为这能为他们节省数十亿美元的风洞测试费用
since it allowed them to save billions of dollars on wind tunnel testing.
这种网上间谍活动的方法持续了多年
This method of online espionage went on for years,
其间苏联人还瞄准了全美各大学的研究项目
and the Soviets also targeted research projects at various universities all across the US
不断将数据传回苏联
constantly funneling the data back to the Soviet Union.
但最终 美国间谍机构还是意识到了这些
But eventually, American spy agencies realized what was going on.
里根总统很快阻止了苏联人从他们的数据库中购买研究论文这一行为
President Reagan quickly stopped the Soviets
from being able to purchase research papers from their databases.
在意识到他们已经泄露了多少重要数据后
After realizing how much important data they had already given away,
他们策划了一个计划 打算破坏苏联航天飞机的设计
they hatched a plan to sabotage the design of the Soviet Space Shuttle.
CIA开始做一些缺陷的航天飞机设计文件提供给苏联人
The CIA began creating flawed Shuttle design documents and fed them to the Soviets,
将它们伪装成最新的改进型设计
disguising them as new and improved designs.
在第一架航天飞机发射2年后 维特洛夫的间谍活动也终于被揭开
2 years after the first Space Shuttle launched, the extent of Ветров spying was finally uncovered.
克格勃在发现他寄给家人的一封信后发现这里竟然还有瓜
The KGB started to suspect something wasn't right
when they found a letter he had sent to his family.
在信中 他一个劲吹自己工作有多么重要
In the letter, he bragged about the importance of his job
还说什么"大的要来了"
and claimed that he was involved in something really big.
但他所做的远不止是窃取航天飞机的设计
But he was doing a lot more than just stealing Space Shuttle designs.
80年代初 他开始窃取其他秘密文件
In the early 80s, he began stealing other secret documents
并提供给法国情报部门
and supplying them to the French intelligence service.
法国总统提醒了罗纳德·里根总统怎么回事
The French president alerted Ronald Reagan of what was going on,
而苏联人很快就查明维特洛夫是一个双面间谍
and the Soviets quickly found out that Ветров was working as a double agent.
克格勃把他带回莫斯科 毙了
The KGB brought him back to Moscow and executed him.
到1981年 美国航天飞机首飞时
By the time, the American Space Shuttle first launched in 1981,
克格勃已获取3000多份与计算机系统和风洞测试有关的文件
the KGB had acquired over 3,000 documents relating to the computer systems and wind tunnel tests.
几年中 苏联人花费了近100万美元(折算为今天的货币)
Over a series of years, the Soviets spent almost $1 million in today's money
追踪获取这些重要的文件
tracking down and obtaining these important documents.
毫无疑问 这为他们节省了数十亿美元和数年的开发时间
There's no doubt that this saved them billions of dollars and years of development.
但遗憾的是 暴风雪号从未像美国航天飞机那样创造历史
But sadly, the Буран never went on to create history like the Space Shuttle did.
尽管在许多方面比航天飞机更强
Despite being more capable than the Shuttle in many ways,
但在1991年苏联解体后 暴风雪项目就被废弃了
the Буран project was completely abandoned after the fall of the Soviet Union in 1991.
暴风雪号的初号机 仅完成一次试飞后
The original Буран, which performed the only test flight
就在停放的机库倒塌后被摧毁
was destroyed when the hangar it was in collapsed.
仅剩的两架原型机则停在拜卡努尔的一个机库里
The only remaining two prototypes are sitting in a hanger in Baikonur.
虽然这两架原型机附近有安保措施
Despite the security surrounding these prototypes,
但还是有很多航天爱好者
many space fans have made the pilgrimage
会穿越哈萨克斯坦的沙漠 潜入这个机库 搞一个朝圣之旅
through the deserts of Kazakhstan to locate and sneak into these hangers.
因此 尽管我们从未看到它发挥其真正的潜力
So although we never got to see it, live out its true potential,
但暴风雪号仍将作为当时最先进的航天器之一而载入史册
the Буран will go down in history as one of the most advanced space vehicles of its time.